A Guide to the Papers of Anne Spencer and the Spencer Family, 1829, 1864-2007
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Correspondence (Box 1-6)
  - 1930-1974 Correspondence - H: Lillian Childress Hall; Eileen Hamilton, M.J. Hamlett; Lillian Harrell, with a poem by her, "The Birthday of a Birth" (December 12, 1938); Professor Gerald Haslan; Frances A. Henson, mentioning the visit by Mary Fox, League for Industrial Democracy (April 16, 1931); Bernice E. [Lomax?] Hill, teacher at the Fontainebleau American Elementary School, describes her trips and teaching experiences, 1956-1958, and local events and controversies in Lynchburg, particularly the construction of two pools, 1964-1965; Edna Holmes; Mrs. John Hope; Danny Howard; Thelma Howard; and the Hutchersons (Box-folder 4:2))
  - 1928-1966, n.d. Correspondence - Langston Hughes, copy of a letter (formerly pinned upon her wall) from Hughes to Anne about letter writing with an original envelope, "You and I are about alike when it comes to letters. I think about them for weeks, then I try to write, - and maybe some of them get written, - but mostly not…" Some of the text is missing from the copy (February 20, 1928); one empty original envelope with his holograph name and address while at Lincoln University [1928?]; Two unsigned pre-printed postal cards advertising Hughes' Troubled Island and the All Negro Poets issue of Voices, A Quarterly of Verse, edited by Langston Hughes (April 7 and December 12, 1949); A typed postal card, signed "Langston" concerning Spencer's poems, "Dunbar" and "Tengo Un Amigo" in the Argentine anthology Dos Siglos De Poesia Norte Americana" and also seeing Alroy the other day (January 4, 1950); a printed postal card with picture of "Africanesque" by Aaron Douglas and printed signature of Langston Hughes on message side (December 1954); news clipping of column by Hughes, "Famous Negro Women of History" in the Chicago Defender, mentioning Anne Spencer, and signed in green ink, "Greetings to you - Langston" (February 22, 1958); press release concerning Something in Common and Other Stories (February 27, 1963); a typed note signed by his assistant concerning a check for the use of Spencer's poetry in La Poesie Negro Americaine (February 18, 1966); undated holograph note signed "Langston" which states, "Loved your letter of last spring. Trains and tours seem to keep me from ever writing. But Happy Holidays to you!" The other side has his printed poem, "Christmas Cards" (formerly pinned upon her wall); and two signed but undated typed manuscripts of his poems, "Barrel House: Chicago" and "Lincoln Theatre: Harlem." Originals of all this material has been placed in the Vault-Hughes box. (Box-folder 4:3))
  - 1923-1969 Correspondence - I-J: Caroline Isham; Thomas Ishell, chaplain in the Marines, requests autographed copies of two of her poems (August 1, 1943); Ella and Billy Jackson; Harold Jackman; Joseph H. Jenkins, Jr. concerning photographs which he had made at Spencer's home and in which Braithwaite has expressed interest (October 20, 1938); Charles S. Johnson, editor of Opportunity, asks Spencer for one or two of her poems for his magazine and quotes a characterization made of Spencer by Georgia Douglas Johnson as "the lofty Amy Lowell type" (December 31, 1923 and October 22, 1924); Will N. Johnson expresses his appreciation for her poem "White Things" published in the March Crisis (March 3, 1923); Harold and Luella Jones; Amy P. Jordan; and M.J. Jordan (Box-folder 4:4))
  - 1933-1967 Correspondence - Altona Trent Johns (1904-1977) and Vernon Johns, discusses her music tour (June 23, 1933); a book by Santayana, Three Philosophical Poets (May 6, 1944); and Vernon's talk to the St. Louis teachers (February 3, 1947). (Box-folder 4:5))
  - 1923-1965, n.d. Correspondence - Georgia Douglas Johnson (1880-1966), mentions the poor health of her husband and her desire to know Anne Spencer (October 28, 1923); apologizes for not telegraphing due to the lateness of the train, etc. and tells Spencer that Dubois and Alice Dunbar, who referred to her as "Anne of the wonderful lines" really wished to meet her (December 12, 1927); always wishes she were closer geographically, "I do not separate you from your garden, your elegant verse and your sure philosophy" (February 24, 1951); and requests a photograph of Spencer to be used in "Singing Brown" by Cedric Dover (n.d.). Johnson also sends printed cards of her poems as Christmas greetings, including: "Brotherhood" (1954); "A Bit of Sky" (1958); "A Little Song" (1960); "The Poet" (1961); "What is Happiness" (1962); "The Poet" (1964); and "Triune" (1965). (Box-folder 4:6))
  - 1919-1955 Correspondence - James Weldon Johnson and Grace Johnson Most of this correspondence is from Grace Johnson. The majority of the Johnson-Spencer correspondence is in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University. Johnson encloses a letter from H.L. Mencken about Anne Spencer's verses, which he asks to be returned (April 3, 1919, copy only); draft of letter to Johnson from Spencer, asks if he has read Mencken's latest in the February Smart Set which she found very amusing and asks what he is writing, "It's going to be a pity if you ever begin thinking that being a Secretary is quite so utilitarian as being a Poet. I would rather have written say, your 'Lottery Girl' or 'Fifty Years' than to have written your Hayti articles, as thoro as they are." (March 2, 1921); a draft from Spencer thanks Johnson for his autographed photograph, looks forward to his visit, discusses a Detroit meeting about Civil Rights, and includes notes to herself about the evils of Jim Crow laws and the damage they do to the Negro soul [April 1921?]; another draft from Spencer discusses the Johnson-Dyer anti-lynching bill, "A natural rider to include in the measure would abolish Jim Crow cars. They are my black beast. Lynching the body is as final as it is undesirable, but the Jim Crow car lynches ones soul over and over again." She also writes about her poetry, "I have nothing new finished. But there are 'leventy-leven bits stuck in as many different places that promise something if I ever get at them." (October 20, 1921 on the back of a Johnson letter dated Sept 24 th); on the back of his letter to her, dated April 14, 1922, where he urges her to continue her writing even if she has to sacrifice everything else, except the welfare of her husband, Anne promises to "take my talents as seriously as a movie-star - or a Baptist preacher." James Johnson sends condolences to Edward on the death of his mother (April 2, 1936); telegram from Rawley Long informing Anne Spencer about the auto accident that killed James Weldon Johnson and seriously injured Grace (June 27, 1938); Grace writes concerning her and others' appreciation and suggestions for the publication of Spencer's poem, "For Jim, Easter Eve" and also the exciting plans for creating a James Weldon Johnson collection at Yale University (November 15, 1947 and n.d.); and recollects her first meeting with Anne Spencer (March 4, 1955). (Box-folder 4:7))
  - 1960-1974, n.d. Correspondence - James Weldon and Grace Johnson, chiefly Christmas greetings from Grace, as James is deceased; Grace recalls their long and satisfying friendship and the poetry during the period represented in Arna Bontemps' American Negro Poetry (September 20, 1963); sends an invitation to the dedication of the James Weldon Johnson Elementary School in New York City, says that Langston Hughes has sent a message to be read and one of his books, and asks if she will send something or some of her children's books for the library (March 18 and May 8, 1966); asks if Anne has published a volume of poems or has a biographical sketch available and explains how Jim and her protégé, Ollie Jewel Sims Okala, who now shares an apartment with her has become like a daughter (July 7, 1966); enthusiastic description of the performance of Pearl Bailey in Hello Dolley [December 19, 1967]; and refers to plans for James Silvera to read Gods Trombones for recording (n.d.) (Box-folder 4:8))
  - 1922-1974 Correspondence - K: Ellen Kaplan; Harry Keeland; and Robert T. Kerlin (Box-folder 4:9))
  - 1942-1963 Correspondence - L: League of American Writers (form letter); Max Lerner; L.O. Lewis; Maggie Lucas; A.H. Lyle; Lynchburg Public Schools, concerning her employment at Dunbar (1946); and the Lynchburg Interracial Commission (Box-folder 4:10))
  - [1923?]-1924 Correspondence - Alain LeRoy Locke (1886-1954), sends a postcard from Berlin, where he met [Claude] McKay, who had just spent seven months in Russia, and talked much about Spencer [August 23, 1923]; and asks Spencer to contribute some of her verses to his The New Negro: An Interpretation published in 1925 (October 20 [1924]). (Box-folder 5:1))
  - 1932-1953 Correspondence - Rawley Long, first husband of Alroy Spencer, chiefly personal and family news, including their divorce (January 2, 1948); attending a Civil Rights rally in New York City (January 13, 1948) (Box-folder 5:2))
  - n.d. Correspondence - Rawley Long, first husband of Alroy Spencer, chiefly personal and family news, includes a story of how much Francis E. Rivers was moved by her poems in James Weldon Johnson's anthology of Negro poetry (n.d.) (Box-folder 5:3))
  - 1931-1975 Correspondence - M: Marshall Chapel; her niece, Mrs. Dollie Mason, asks advice about some antiques she has purchased (June 2 and [November 1, 1943]); Ruth Mayer; Harry M. Meacham, congratulates her on her 94 th birthday (April 19, 1974) and mentions hearing from Murrell Edmunds (January 20, 1975); Dot Spencer Meade; Hazel Moon; Monroe E. Moon; Connie Houda Moore; Evelyn L. Moore; Charles Satchell Morris II; Robert Morrison; Gay Morrow; Clarence Muse, actor (1889-1979), note on a family newsletter (August 1971) (Box-folder 5:4))
  - 1931-1975 Correspondence - M: Marshall Chapel; her niece, Mrs. Dollie Mason, asks advice about some antiques she has purchased (June 2 and [November 1, 1943]); Ruth Mayer; Harry M. Meacham, congratulates her on her 94 th birthday (April 19, 1974) and mentions hearing from Murrell Edmunds (January 20, 1975); Dot Spencer Meade; Hazel Moon; Monroe E. Moon; Connie Houda Moore; Evelyn L. Moore; Charles Satchell Morris II; Robert Morrison; Gay Morrow; Clarence Muse, actor (1889-1979), note on a family newsletter (August 1971) (Box-folder 5:4))
  - 1937-1969 Correspondence - Mc: Medora MacLaren; and Carolyn McPherson, thanking her for the copy of the poem "If Ever a Garden" (January 11, 1937) (Box-folder 5:5))
  - 1939-1976, n.d. Correspondence - Amaza L. Meredith, artist and former head of the Art Department at Virginia State College, Petersburg, Virginia (1895-1984), including greeting cards, programs, and letters, some illustrated with her artwork (Box-folder 5:6))
  - 1926-1974 Correspondence - N-O: National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, asking Anne Spencer to gather some people who might be interested in reorganizing the local Lynchburg branch (March 15, 1926); National Trade and Professional School for Women and Girls; Effie Lee Newsome; Ross W. Newsome; Mary Noechel; Ollie Jewell Sims Okala, including a poem by her husband Etuka Okala, "Anniversary Piece" about James Weldon Johnson (March 12, 1948); condolences on the death of Edward Spencer (June 16, 1964) (Box-folder 5:7))
  - 1935-1974 Correspondence - P: including Lucille Dixie Palmer; Dan Payne, asking for information about John Chilembwe (March 28, 1958); Letitia Penn; Margaret Perry; George W. Peyton; Pioneer Bible Class; Poindexter family; Idella Purnell, who accepted "Lines to a Nasturium" for her Negro Poets number of Palms (June 26, 1926) (Box-folder 5:8))
  - 1927-1974 Correspondence - R: Georgia Reed; Pearl E. Reed; Dr. and Mrs. F.F. Richards; Billie Rivers; Pearl Virginia Robinson; Francis Coleman Rosenberger, requesting some of her poetry to reprint in his collection of Virginia poetry (January 23, February 7, 18, and October 22, 1947); and Louis D. Rubin, Jr. about Lee Greene's work on Anne Spencer (1974) (Box-folder 5:9))
  - 1961 Mar-Sep Correspondence - Recording of God's Trombones (Box-folder 5:10))
  - 1939-1973 Correspondence - S: Satellite Class; Private Hillary Scott (April 7 and November 5, 1943); Hattie Scott; Professor George Shepperson, concerning her classmate at Virginia Theological Seminary, John Chilembwe (January 13 and February 21, 1954; July 22 and 30, 1959); Katie Pryor Smith; Ruth Moore Smith; Carrie Trotter Spencer; Edward Spencer postcard (1939); Garnell Stamps; and Carolyn Stewart (Box-folder 5:11))
  - n.d. Correspondence - Anne Spencer Drafts includes: Condolences, Greetings and Miscellaneous Drafts, including one to "Dear Poets" alerting them to her sudden departure to the doctor and her hope to return shortly. (Box-folder 5:12))
  - 1942-1970, n.d. Correspondence - Anne Spencer Drafts includes: Letters to the Editor of Several Newspapers, including the topics of Virginius Dabney (n.d.), Adam Clayton Powell (n.d.); amount and position of space allotted to murder story as opposed to the death of Admiral Richard Byrd (n.d.); humorous story for Reader's Digest (n.d.); the injustice of Jim Crow laws and the Acts of the Assembly of Virginia (n.d.); the incompatibility of the Selective Service Act and non-integration (n.d.); the loss of [Martin Luther King?] or some other strong leader (n.d.); death of Eleanor Roosevelt November 8, [1962]; expression of gratitude for a letter to the Editor written by Mr. Callahan (1963); and a letter to Richmond Times Dispatch (July 2, 1942). (Box-folder 5:13))
    Letters to Publishers, including a long draft to Mr. Bosler about the possibility of publishing a book of her work, in which she says "I don't negate my poems - they are me in the years here they are my conversation with myself" (n.d.); drafts to Mr. Ferrone concerning possible publication of her work, "For over 70 years my pencil has sought a scrap of paper - to tell the bees, so to speak, and the habit saves from whatever local aridity I would suffer - hence I try to tell my truth as I do accept the truth of those who have reverence for it" and suggests Sterling Brown, Dr. Helen Edmunds, or Dr. Ben Fuson for writing the preface (1970 March, n.d.); "Darling Critic" explaining "Once I wrote some lines - 'I Have a Friend.' I was sitting in while a lovely lady explain[ed] to the group 'she means God.' I said later and meanly, I was not excluding God. I was trying of course to memorialize memory itself not had but have - About the other pieces you ask to use, please take part of sketch from Cullen's Caroling Dusk" (n.d.); a draft to "Gentlemen" giving some information about herself (May 21, 1963); an unaddressed note giving permission to use her poems mentioned in their letter and correcting the place of her birth (n.d.); and a draft to Mr. Amory of the [Saturday Review?] discussing Ellen Glasgow, James Branch Cabell, and racism, "the Negro knows the white man wherever he occurs better than the white know himself: we have tracked him down into his secret recesses where he had not take a look for a long three centuries," and continues "Through an inheritance from that great people the Jew He had given the world His Especial Image, Jesus, they grabbed the Image and began at once to pogromize the giver" (n.d.)
  - 1926-1958, n.d. Correspondence - Anne Spencer Drafts to Individuals includes: drafts to Mr. Beecham, supplying biographical information (n.d.); asks Andrew [Burris?] if he would take an interest in a boy she knows who wants to write plays (n.d.); refers to Arthur Paul Davis (1904-1996) column, "With a Grain of Salt," in the Norfolk Journal and Guide that reminded her of a friend, Mary (n.d.) and thanks him for a copy of his book [The New Cavalcade: African American Writing from 1760 to the Present and The New Cavalcade II ?] (n.d.); James Evans (January 22, 1858); Mrs. Harris, writes a letter in response to her "Black and White" in the Post from her position as a female Negro (n.d.); Robert Herbert, appreciates his poems (Sep 15, [n.y.]; Mr. Lerner, listing some "illusionary history" facts (n.d.); to Mr. McKay, sends him copies of her poems, "White Things" and "To a Nasturtium" which she likes better than anything else that she has done. "White Things' I have tried to make gather up a caustic momentum as it rolls along a la McKay!" (n.d.); Mrs. Carol Paradise, Norton, permission to use her poems and advising her about biographical sketches (n.d.); Mr. [William] Raspberry on politics and his column "Potomac Watch" (n.d.); Miss Harriet E. Robinson, Harper and Brothers, giving permission to use her poems "At the Carnival" and "Questing" in Professor Joseph Smith's revised Fundamentals of Speech (n.d.); Rosa Tatum, Mr. Truman, takes the former president to task for his description of the Selma March as "silly" and gives her own opinion of the march (n.d.); Mr. N.O. White, responds to his letter to her which shows a complete misunderstanding of her as a person (November 18, 1947); and Mr. C.V. Wilson, Lynchburg, asks if local lodges and other organizations could raise money to help ameliorate the deplorable living conditions of the south-west American Indians (December 30, 1947). (Box-folder 6:1))
  - 1926-1972 Correspondence - T: Katherine [Rosa?] Tatum, at her request, Anne Spencer furnishes some information about her life for her master's thesis at the University of Oklahoma, "Mr. Johnson himself found me. He came walking through our woods one day and picked me up. A risky thing to do. My tastes are likely considered plebian by many 'Best People': I love - I mean love till it hurts - being a Negro woman. I love a Negro man [whom I married] twenty-five years ago. He is that rare creature with an understanding heart. You see, no dream can live unless somebody lets it live - or die unless the somebody kills it." She goes on to describe how she personally copes with Jim Crow laws (March 9, 1926); Alice Taylor; This Week Magazine Editor William I. Nichols, Anne Spencer had sent a copy of her poem about James Weldon Johnson for publication on the tenth anniversary of his death but was turned down (May 24, 1948); Em Thompson (postcards); Mrs. H.E. Thompson; Thelma Thornhill; Hortense E. Thornton; Howard Thurman (1900-1981); Sue [Bailey Thurman] asks Spencer to contribute to The Historical Cookbook of the American Negro in honor of James Weldon Johnson [October 1958]; S.W. Tucker; and Twin City Library Club, Bristol, Tennessee-Virginia (Box-folder 6:2))
  - 1949, 1964 Correspondence - Telegrams, all but one expressing condolences upon the death of Edward A. Spencer (1964) (Box-folder 6:3))
  - 1938-1953 Correspondence - U-V, including: United Asia; Carl Van Vechten, thanking Spencer for sending her letters from James Weldon Johnson to the library at Yale (July 27, 1942; June 22, 1943); and Virginia Union University request for donation (October 25, 1938 and May 9, 1941) (Box-folder 6:4))
  - 1931-1965 Correspondence - Unidentified, including: a speech by Georgia Douglas Johnson at the American Interracial Seminar dinner (January 15, 1931); and a thesis on the development of the Negro woman in poetry (July 20, 1944) (Box-folder 6:5))
  - 1966-1973, n.d. Correspondence - Unidentified (Box-folder 6:6))
  - 1940-1966 Correspondence - Unidentified (Postcards) (Box-folder 6:7))
  - 1965-1976 Correspondence - University of Virginia and Other Institutions seeking the papers of Anne Spencer, including Howard University, Library of Congress, Virginia Historical Society, University of North Carolina (Box-folder 6:8))
  - 1956-1976 Correspondence - Virginia Theological Seminary and College (Box-folder 6:9))
  - 1943-1975 Correspondence - W, including: C.S. Warren; Odell M. Washington; James and Elizabeth Watkins; Eleanor Wheatland; Freda White; Violet Wilson; Paula Winder; Dr. Max Winsor; the Reverend Virgil A. Wood; the Woodruffs; Arlene M. Woods; and Rosa J. Woodard (Box-folder 6:10))
  - 1926-1940 Correspondence - Walter White, advises Spencer to read Willa Cather's "My Mortal Enemy" for an example of what she could do with her story (November 10, 1926); sends her copies of "My Mortal Enemy" by Cather and "Far End" by May Sinclair (November 19, 1926); thanks Spencer for the first donation to the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Fund, which has she suggested (June 29 1938 and March 21, 1940) (Box-folder 6:11))
  - 1942-1943 Correspondence - X, Y, Z, including: Madie Hall Xuma establishing women's clubs in South Africa and her research in the connection between African music and the Negro Spirituals (August 1, 1943); Yale University receipt for the correspondence of Anne Spencer from James Weldon Johnson (August 11 and 13, 1942) (Box-folder 6:12))
- Photographs (Box-folder 7:1-9:9)
  - n.d. Photograph - Bessie Alexander (Box-folder 7:1))
  - n.d. Photograph - Mae Alexander and family of [Dr. Alexander?] (Box-folder 7:2))
  - n.d. Photograph - Rosemary Allen, with her nurse (Box-folder 7:3))
  - n.d. Photograph - Mack Anderson, husband of Aunt Betty Spencer (1876-1948) (Box-folder 7:4))
  - 1873, n.d. Photograph - Joel Cephus Bannister (Box-folder 7:5))
  - n.d. Photograph - Mamie Bondurant, age 18 (Box-folder 7:6))
  - n.d. Photograph - Nannie Bondurant (age 10); Louise Bondurant (age 4); and Mamie Bondurant (age 8), left to right, daughters of Edward Alexander Bondurant (Box-folder 7:7))
  - n.d. Photograph - Reginald Bondurant, age 16 (Box-folder 7:8))
  - 1919 May 4 Photograph - Richard Gordon Bondurant in uniform, age 20 (Box-folder 7:9))
  - n.d. Photograph - Bondurant children (Box-folder 7:10))
  - n.d. Photograph - Captain Charles Breck (Box-folder 7:11))
  - n.d. Photograph - Elsie Brown, Bramwell, West Virginia (Box-folder 7:12))
  - [1907] Photograph - Leo Burke (Box-folder 7:13))
  - n.d. Photograph - William Calloway, "Uncle Cal," with Bethel Calloway and Alroy Sarah Spencer (Box-folder 7:14))
  - 1958, 1961, n.d. Photograph - Children and Babies, including two class photographs for Kindergarten and Fourth Grade, Harding School, San Bernadino, California, and great-grandchildren of Anne and Edward Spencer (Box-folder 7:15))
  - n.d. Photograph - John Davies (Box-folder 7:16))
  - 1893, n.d. Photograph - Sarah Louise Scales Bannister Dickerson, mother of Anne Spencer (Box-folder 7:17))
  - 1975 Photograph - Albert J. Dunmore (Box-folder 7:18))
  - n.d. Photograph - "Edankraal," also includes a sketch (Box-folder 7:19))
  - n.d. Photograph - J.B. Evans and granddaughter (Box-folder 7:20))
  - n.d. Photograph - Muriel Fawcett (Box-folder 7:21))
  - n.d. Photograph - Ophelia Spencer Fisher, sister of Edward (Box-folder 7:22))
  - n.d. Photograph - Mrs. Fox, Dean of Women at Virginia Theological Seminary and College (Box-folder 7:23))
  - 1929-1954 Photograph - Garden of Anne and Edward Spencer, including photograph of Anne and Edward Spencer, Edward Spencer II, and Mrs. Fuson (Box-folder 7:24))
  - 1974 Photograph - Cynthia Granger (1957?- ), Model in "The Anne Spencer Story" (Box-folder 7:25))
  - n.d. Photograph - Sister Louise Harris (Box-folder 7:26))
  - 1894-1900, n.d. Photograph - Gregory Hayes (d. 1906) and Mary Rice Hayes (1875-1935), later married William Patterson Allen (Box-folder 7:27))
  - n.d. Photograph - Mabel and Minnie Hayes (Box-folder 7:28))
  - n.d. Photograph - Mary George Hill (Box-folder 7:29))
  - [1895], 1911 Photograph - Pearl Hobson (Box-folder 7:30))
  - [1918] Photograph - Celinda Wright Humbles (1887-1976), her father worked at Virginia Theological Seminary (Box-folder 7:31))
  - Photograph - Iris Elvira Jackson [1907?]-1997, Chauncey Spencer's first wife n.d. (Box-folder 7:32))
  - [1921?] Apr 14 Photograph - James Weldon Johnson (Box-folder 7:33))
  - n.d. Photograph - Dorothy Jones (Box-folder 7:34))
  - n.d. Photograph - Marietta Spencer Jones (1886-1947) and her husband (Box-folder 7:35))